Imagine a T-shaped intersection.
设想一个 T 型路口
The blue self-driving car pulls up to that stop sign and would
蓝色无人驾驶汽车在停车标志处停下
like to make a left turn but it sees this green car coming from the left.
蓝车想左转 但是它看到这辆绿车从左边过来了
If the green car is turning right,
如果绿车要右转
it is safe for the blue car to go.
那么蓝车可以安全左转
But if the green car is going straight,
但是如果绿车直行
then the blue car should wait.
那么蓝车应该等待
The way we would handle this with the model based approach is as follows.
下面我们讲一下如何使用基于模型法处理这种情况
First we would come up with two process models,
首先 这里涉及到两个过程模型
one for going straight and one for turning right.
直行过程模型和右转过程模型
And we would use some simple trajectory generator to figure out
我们将使用一些简单轨迹生成器来绘出
what trajectory we would expect to see if
当驾驶员直行或者右转时
the driver were going straight or turning right.
我们的预期轨迹
Then we would pay attention to the actual behavior of the target vehicle and using
接下来 我们将把注意力放在目标车辆的实际行为上
a multimodal estimation algorithm which is still a black box for now we would
并使用一个当前还是个黑盒子的多模估量算法
compare observed trajectory to the ones we would expect for each of our models.
我们将对比观察的轨迹与每个模块中我们预期生成的轨迹
And then based on that we would
接下来 基于上述对比
assign a probability to each of the possible trajectories.
我们将为每一条可能轨迹赋予一个几率
But the important takeaway for purely model based prediction is that we
纯粹的基于模型法有时候很方便
have some bank of possible behaviors and each has a mathematical model of
前提是我们有一批可能的行为
motion which takes into account the physical capabilities of the object as well
并且为每种行为建立了运动数学模型
as the constraints imposed by the road traffic laws and other restrictions.
模型建立时 已经将目标车辆的物理限制、道路交规以及其他限制考虑在内
What about a data driven approach.
数据驱动法又如何呢
Well with the purely data driven approach we have
通过使用纯粹的数据驱动法
a truly blackbox algorithm and this algorithm will be trained on lots of training data.
我们就有了一个真正的黑盒算法 该算法会通过大量训练数据来训练
Once it's trained we just fitted
一旦训练完毕
the observed behavior and let it make a prediction about what will happen next.
我们会把观察到的行为输入其中 让算法来生成接下来如何行动的预测
So we can see that each approach has its own strengths.
所以我们可以看出 每种方法各有所长
Model based approaches incorporate our knowledge of
基于模型方法吸收了我们有关物理限制的知识
physics constraints imposed by the road traffic et cetera and
这些知识来自于道路交通情况等等
data driven approaches are nice because they let us use data to
同时 数据驱动法也很不错 因为它们使我们使用数据
extract subtle patterns that would otherwise be missed by model based approaches.
来抽取潜在模式 这是基于模型法所缺少的
For example differences in
例如
vehicle behavior at an intersection during different times of the day.
每天不同时段在一个交叉路口的汽车的不同行为
And this leads to the somewhat leading question.
这就引发了一个可以说很重要的问题
Which approach is the best.
那就是 哪种方法是最好的？